The Archives of Atlantic Monthly 0057.LIT
Special Collections and University Archives
Archives of the Atlantic Monthly
1966-1980
1976-1980
Special Collections and University Archives
Atlantic Monthly
0057.LIT
0.25 Linear Feet
The Atlantic Monthly Press was founded in 1917 as the publishing division of the Atlantic Monthly Company. The press was originally envisioned by Editor Ellery Sedwick as a vehicle for publishing books based on articles and essays originally printed in the Atlantic Monthly magazine, but struggled in its early years and was eventually acquired as an imprint by Little, Brown and Co. The press was responsible for publishing Katherine Anne Porter's Ship of Fools (1962) and The Never Ending Wrong (1977), and many of the staff members of the press, such as Associate Editor Seymour Lawrence, were friends and confidantes of Porter. The collection consists primarily of correspondence with Katherine Anne Porter, as well as with people and institutions involved with the production and promotion of her work. Also included in the collection are articles and clippings relating to Porter, invoices, and royalty statements.
Use and Access to Collection
This collection is open for research.
Custodial History and Acquisition Information
The Archives of the Atlantic Monthly Press came to the University of Maryland Libraries through the efforts of Peter Davison in January 2002. In 1986 the then-owner of the Atlantic Monthly, Morton Zuckerman, sold the book division of the Atlantic Monthly Company to Carl Navarre, who in turn sold the press to Morgan Entrekin in 1991. Entrekin tired of warehousing the archives and subsequently returned the materials to Atlantic Monthly at the request of its staff. Since their return, Davison has placed these archival materials with institutions housing the major archives of the individual authors. Davison was director of the Atlantic Monthly Press from 1964 to 1979 and senior editor from 1979 to 1985. From 1964 until Porter's death, Davison was responsible for maintaining relations with Porter and Atlantic Monthly Press. He has also edited and published books with Houghton Mifflin under the Peter Davison Books imprint (1985-1998). In 2002, he was the poetry editor of the Atlantic Monthly.
Scope and Content of Collection
The archives of Atlantic Monthly Press span the years 1966 to 1980. Much of the collection consists of correspondence with Katherine Anne Porter, as well as individuals and institutions involved in the promotion and publication of Porter's work. Additionally, the collection includes articles and clippings, invoices, and royalty statements.
Arrangement
The materials are organized in one series
Series 1: Correspondence
Related Material
Materials related to the Atlantic Monthly Press Papers can be found in the Papers of Katherine Anne Porter, the Papers of Seymour Lawrence, the Papers of Cyrilly Abels, and the Papers of Paul Porter in the Special Collections of the University of Maryland Libraries. Additional materials can be found in the Seymour Lawrence Publishing Archive at the University of Mississippi Department of Special Collections and the Seymour Lawrence Files related to Kurt Vonnegut at the University of Delaware Department of Special Collections.
For other related archival and manuscript collections, please see the following
subject guides
.
Authors and Publishers -- Archival Resources; Katherine Anne Porter -- 1890-1980 -- Correspondence; Atlantic Monthly Press -- Archives; Katherine Anne Porter -- 1890-1980; Cyrilly Abels; Peter Davidson
- Correspondence, 1966-1980; 1; 232 items
  Scope and Contents
  This series consists of correspondence from and relating to Katherine Anne Porter and the work she published with the Atlantic Monthly Press. It includes originals, carbons, and photocopies of letters, invoices, and royalty statements, and clippings from serial publications. The series is arranged chronologically. Significant correspondents represented in the collection include Katherine Anne Porter, Peter Davison, Cyrilly Abels, and Paul Porter.
  - Correspondence, 1966; 1.1.1 (Box 1, Folder 1.0)
  - Correspondence, 1967; 1.1.2 (Box 1, Folder 2.0)
  - Correspondence, 1968; 1.1.3 (Box 1, Folder 3.0)
  - Correspondence, 1969; 1.1.4 (Box 1, Folder 4.0)
  - Correspondence, 1970; 1.1.5 (Box 1, Folder 5.0)
  - Correspondence, 1971; 1.1.6 (Box 1, Folder 6.0)
  - Correspondence, 1972; 1.1.7 (Box 1, Folder 7.0)
  - Correspondence, 1973; 1.1.8 (Box 1, Folder 8.0)
  - Correspondence, 1974; 1.1.9 (Box 1, Folder 9.0)
  - Correspondence, 1975; 1.1.10 (Box 1, Folder 10.0)
  - Correspondence, 1976; 1.1.11 (Box 1, Folder 11.0)
  - Correspondence, 1977; 1.1.12 (Box 1, Folder 12.0)
  - Correspondence, 1978; 1.1.13 (Box 1, Folder 13.0)
  - Correspondence, 1979; 1.1.14 (Box 1, Folder 14.0)
  - Correspondence, 1980; 1.1.15 (Box 1, Folder 15.0)